Juan Manuel Paiba | C.V.

Bogotá D.C – Colombia Data Scientist/Data Engineer/Data Analytics Lead

☐ 350 6322888 • ☑ jmpaiba123@gmail.com ③ www.linkedin.com/in/juan-manuel-paiba-amaya-82a87735

Data professional with more than 6 years of total experience in data science, marketing and finance. Also, skilled in machine learning, data science, applied math, econometrics, probability, game theory. Worked on theory and data analytics on stochastic process on pricing models. Looking forward for a technical role where i can solve the complex challenges for the customers and also team member.

Previous Employment

Movistar (Telefónica Hispam)

Bogotá D.C

Sr. Data Science Specialist

January 2023 - Ongoing

Consulting in the analytical area of billing, profitability, and collections is being conducted through data analysis and mining with the aim of optimizing the profitability of the sale process for technology equipment in installments. This process is being carried out by consulting and generating structured data in Teradata. The analysis is being developed using Python, PyCaret, and classification models, managing to identify the details of the negative aspects of the portfolio, which could improve the profitability of this line of business by up to 10 percent. Financial and operational metrics are being captured to measure the impact of creating the data science and machine learning solution

Directy Latinoamerica

Bogotá D.C

Forecasting, Scoring and Data Scientist

July 2017 - December 2022

Construction and implementation of collection models for dtv latam (classification models), using new machine learning methodologies (light-gbm) using python, oracle cloud and git repositories, The previously mentioned work had a positive impact on the recovery of the debt collection, as a higher amount was recovered more quickly. Review and maintenance of income score models for the northern region. KPI's Forecasting in order to support stakeholders decisions. Data cleaning, feature engineering, and model evaluation focused to produce benefit in company, or reduce losses. Important achievement: Analytic development for implementation of current customer retention structure in DTV Colombia, which is based on customer lifetime value.

Data and Marketing Consultant-Ubina Consulting

Tunja, Boyacá

Jr.Analyst

February 2016 - June 2017

Refinement, organization, and database analysis related with customer marketing, in order to provide technical information and clear support to our investors. Important achievement: Process data automation using programming languages, VBA(visual basic), R and Python

Education

Academic Qualifications.

0	Universitat de Barcelona Master Big Data y Data Science,	Bogotá D.C 2022-2023
0	Massachusetts Institute of Technology No Code AI and ML: Building Data Science Solutions, Quantitative approach	Online Program 2022
0	Externado University Finance master, Quantitative approach	Bogotá D.C 2018-2021
0	Andes University Mathematician,	Bogotá D.C 2007-2012
0	Seminario Diocesano School Higschool,	Duitama 1995-2006

Academic achievements and Courses.

Excelent English Skills: speaking, listening, writing and ready Upper intermediate level: B2 ,Andes University courses, finance risk modeling: Exchange risk, credit risk, regulation and institutions, Andes University, 2018. Introduction to time series with R application. UPTC, Tunja, 2016. Scholarship given to excellent students (Best ICFES results in Colombia) without sources to pay first level college. Andes University, Bogotá, 2006.

Technical and Personal skills

- Programming Languages: R, VBA(Intermedio), SQL(Advanced), Python (Advanced), TeX, SAS (Advanced), Spark, Hadoop, MongoDB
- Industry Software Skills: PowerPoint (Advanced), Matlab (Advanced), Excel (Advanced),
 Power BI (Advanced), Derive.
- o **Applied math:** Statistics, stochastics process, graph theory, game theory, cryptography, econometrics, machine learning (supervised and unsupervise methods), business analytics
- Machine Learning Algorithms and Analytics: Linear and Logistic Regression, Decision trees, Bagging, Boosting, Clustering, K-means, PCA. Time series: AR, MA, ARIMA, stochastic process. Recommendation Systems. Deep Learning Algorithms: DNN, CNN. Nocode tools: Rapid Miner, databricks.
- o Personal skills: team working and excellent professional relationships

References

- o Ernesto Ramirez, Analytics Director DTV, tel: 3208656135
- o Michael Patiño, Lead Data Scientist at Millicom Tigo, tel: 3023001306